Register of the René Lemarchand papers, 1916-1973
Hoover Institution Archives
René Lemarchand papers
1916-1973
72012
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes, 2 microfilm reels (1.5 linear feet)
Government reports, ephemeral publications, interviews, correspondence, notes, and printed matter relating to the political development of the Congo, Burundi, and Rwanda.
Lemarchand, René, 1932-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1972.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Government reports, ephemeral publications, interviews, correspondence, notes, and printed matter relating to the political development of the Congo, Burundi, and Rwanda.
Biographical Note
French-American political scientist.
Africa, Central.; Africa.; Burundi.; Congo (Democratic Republic); Rwanda.
- Burundi File
  - Official documents (Box 1)
    - 1) Ecole Royale d'Administration Publique et de Gestion des Affaires: Ses buts, son organisation, Bujumbura, n.p., undated; 7 p.
    - 2) Urundi, Territoire de Muhinga Enquête Administrative Générale de 1929, by Hendrick, Muhinga, 1929 November 14; 17 p.
    - 3) Urundi, Territoire de Rumonge, Enquête Administrative Générale, n.p., undated; 23 p.
    - 4) Administration Indigène, "Note" summing up exchange between Résident Schmidt and Messrs. Laurentie, Woodbridge and De la Roche, of the UN Trusteeship Visiting Mission, n.p., undated; 10 p.
    - 5) Notes Concernant l'Origine et les Droits du Chef Kirima et de sa Famille, D'après un Rapport de M.L. De Lannoy, Substitut de l'Auditeur Militaire, Kitega, (Texte remanié et résumé, J.M.D. (Jean-Marie Derscheid), d'après l'original communiqué par M. Ryekmans), Bruxelles, 1934 September; 3 p.
    - 6) Observations sur le Rapport Politique du 1er Trimestre (Extrait d'un Rapport de M.P. Ryckmans, 1er Trimestre), 1918; 2 p.
    - 7) Répercussions Politiques de la Vie Privée de Mwambutsa, by Résident Robert Schmidt, 1953 February; 3 p.
    - 8) Abatare et Abezi, by Resident Robert Schmidt, 1953 February-May; 15 p.
    - 9) Exchange Correspondence between Vice-Gouverneur General and Resident re "Affaire Somme Manquante Souscription Mwami," Kitega, 1951 August 6; 9 p.
  - Monographs
    - 10) J. Ghislain, Chronologic Politique du Burundi, n.p., from page 32 to 55 only, undated (1961?)
    - 11) Paul Mirerekano, Ebwire Gito Canje... ("Listen, my son..."), n.p., typescript of translation into French by J. Ghislain, plus Note au sujet de la traduetion de Mbwire Gito Canje, Usumbure, undated, 1962 April 5; 23 p.
    - 12) A. Keuppens, Le Burundi Ancien et Moderne: Esquisse Historique, Usumbura, pp. 41., 1964
  - Ephemeral materials (tracts, petitions, etc.)
    - 13) Uneba, Résolutions du Séminaire National Organisé par l'Union Nationale des Etudiants Barundi, Bujumbura, 1963 August 25-31; 31 p.
    - 14) Uneba, Cinquieme Congress Organise par l'Uneba du 26 au 31 aout 1964, circa 1964; 45 p.
    - 15) Programme du Rassemblement Populaire Africain du Burundi..., 1962 April 20; 3 p.
    - 16) La Position de l'Uprona devant la Résolution du Colloque Belgique--Urundi au sujet des princes Barundi, 1960 September 5; 3 p.
    - 17) Lettre de l'Uprona au Resident de l'urundi, 1960 July 23; 3 p.
    - 18) Droit de Réponse au Texte de Mr. Harroy..., undated; 1 p.
    - 19) Communiqué No. 1, Prise de Position de l'Uprona, 1960 August 14; 2 p.
    - 20) Démenti des faux-bruits, réponse au tract Ukwikukira répandu par l'Uprona en territoire de Bururi, 1960 September; 3 p.
    - 21) Motion adressée à la mission de visite de l'ONU par le Parti "Mouvement Progressiste du Burundi,", 1960 March 29; 4 p.
    - 22) Manifeste de l'Union Eurafricaine du Ruanda Urundi, 1960 September 14; 2 p.
    - 23) Anonymous, To Oni's Mission Counsel in the peregrination (sic), n.p., undated; 1 p.
    - 24) Lettre des Presidents des partis P.P., P.E.P., etc..., 1960 September 16; 1 p.
    - 25) Petition adressée à la Mission de Visite du Conseil de Tutelle des Nations Unies, signed "de nombreux Barundi,", 1957 October 10; 8 p.
    - 26) Note à l'Occasion de la Visite du Groupe de Travail au Burundi, by Joseph Ntidendereza, 1959 April 25; 12 p.
    - 27) Petition adressée à la Mission de Visite du Conseil de Tutelle...Kitega, 1957 September 23; 5 p.
    - 28) Communiqué des évolués de Burundi aux commissions intérimaire et électorale, 1960 June 26; 2 p.
    - 29) Uprona, Lettre à Monsieur le Résident Général, Usumbura, 1960 March 29; 3 p.
    - 30) Lettre à Sa Majesté le Roi du Burundi, from "les membres du Bureau de l'Assemblee Nationale,", 1964 March 12; 2 p.
    - 31) Lettre à Sa Majesté le Roi du Burundi, Objet: Situation politique actuelle, from Siryuyumunsi, Sineremera, Bucumi, 1964 February 15; 2 p.
    - 32) Réponse à la "Note sur le Climat Politique à l'Approche des Elections," Bruxelles, 1960 September 5; 6 p.
    - 33) Mise au Point du Prince Louis Rwagasore, 1960 September 3; 2 p.
    - 34) Tract signé "Les Gens de Bururi,", 1960 September 23; 2 p.
    - 35) Uneba(?), excerpt from "Les Barundi à leurs amis étrangers," n.p., undated; 8 p.
    - 36) Letter of J.B. Ntitendereza to Le Résident de l'Urundi, Muramvya, 1946 February 20; 9 p.
    - 37) Chant des Abadasinga du Burundi, n.p., undated; 2 p.
    - 38) Uprona (Abadasigana), Lettre à Monsieur le Président de la Mission de Visite du Conseil de Tutelle de Passage à Kitega, undated; 4 p.
    - 39) Joseph Cimpaye, Les premiers battements d'ailes: Le Burundi face à son destin (Analysis of post-independence politics in Burundi), n.p., undated; 18 p.
    - 40) Anonymous, Composition des Equipes Gouvernementales qui se sont succédées depuis l'autonomie interne (1961) juseu'a ce jour, n.p., undated; 3 p.
    - 41) Rapport d'Ordre 624 du 21 mai 1965 (Sûreté), période du 15 au 21 mai, n.p., undated; 3 p.
    - 42) Ordonnance législative No. 07/1/77 du 8 Mars 1961, Fixant les principes généraux de la fonction publique au Burundi, 8 p.
    - 43) Royaume du Burundi, Sénat, Motion adressée à Sa Majesté le Roi du Burundi concernant les élections communales, No. 010/1, 1965 September 28; 3 p.
    - 44) Tract, signed, Manege Francois, Barundi Mwese... (plus translation), n.p., undated; 2 p.
    - 45) Christian Mushatsi-Kareba, President du R.P.A., "Aperçu de la Situation Politique au Burundi depuis le 18 septembre 1961,", 1962 May 4; 5 p.
    - 46) Ibid., "L'Echo du Burundi: L'Asservissement de la Masse-Hutu aux Seigneure Tutsi,", 1962 May; 4 p.
    - 47) Uneba, Letter to His Majesty Mwambutsa IV, Bruxelles, 1965 February 10; 2 p.
    - 48) F. Preziozi, "New Government in Burundi," to the UN High Commissioner, Bukavu, 1963 July 9; 2 p.
    - 49) Colloque du Burundi, 1960 August 31; 6 p.
    - 50) Deuxième Manifeste du Parti Politique, "Unité et Progrès National du Burundi" (Uprona), n.p., undated (late 1961?); 1 p.
    - 51) Note sur le Climat Politique à l'Approche des Elections, 1960 July; 7 p.
    - 52) Programme du Parti Démocrate Chrétien du Burundi, n.p., undated; 4 p.
  - Newspapers and periodicals
    - 53) Translations from Ndongozi (French), various issues
  - Interviews and other documents
    - 54) No. 020/1171/010, Transmis copie pour information à: Monsieur le Chef de Cabinet du Roi à Bujumbura, à Monsieur le Premier Vice-President de l'Assemblée Nationale à Bujumbura, 1964 October 1
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes declassified records returned to file after October 2015 release by Hoover.
    - 55) (UNEBA) Etat de Questions, "droit constitutionnel", 19 p.
    - 56) Account of the Hutu-led abortive coup of October 1965 by Cdt. Lienart, circa 1965; 2 p.
    - 57) Interview, Pascal Bubiriza, 3 p.
    - 58) Interview, Ngendadumwe, re Crise Uprona, 1 p.
    - 59) Interview, Ntiruwhama, 3 p.
    - 60) Interview, Ntahokaja, J.B. (Abbe)
    - 61) Fiche biographique, Nugu, Andre
    - 62) Zenon Nicayenzi: Directeur Général à la Coordination
    - 63) Interview, Paul Mirerekano
    - 64) Interview, Bimazubute
    - 65) Interview, Gervais Chinza
    - 66) Interview, Emmanuel Nigane
    - 67) Mémorandum du Mouvement Populaire Chrétien, 1962 January (?)
    - 68) Interview, Leon Manwangari, 3 p.
    - 69) Fiche biographique, Albin Nyamoya
    - 70) Fiche biographique, Pierre Ngendadumwe
    - 71) Interview, Pie Masombuko
    - 72) Fiche biographique, Andre Muhirwa
    - 73) Interview, Baranyanka
    - 74) Histoire de la famille des Ntare (Andre Muhirwa)
    - 75) Interview, Barusasyeko
    - 76) General situation in Burundi from April 29 to May 14, 1972, circa 1972
    - 77) Allgemeine Lage in Burundi vom 29 April - 14 Mai 1972, circa 1972
    - 78) Letters to Pierre Jacques: letter to P. Jacques from A. Molitor, Chef de Cabinet du Roi, 14 février; letter to A. Molitor from P. Jacques, 22 février; letter to Rene Lemarchand from P. Jacques, 17 février; letter to P. Jacques from Universite Officielle de Bujumbura, 1973
    - 79) Composition du Gouvernement de la Rep. du Burundi constitute le 14 juillet 1972, circa 1972
    - 80) Communiqué de Presse, 1972 August 8
    - 81) Letter to Francois Maceri from P. Jacques, 5 sept.; letter from John Storm Roberts (Africa Report) to P. Jacques, 31 jan., 1972, 1973
- Congo File
  - 1) UMHK (Union Miniére du Haut Katanga), Département MOI, Instruction de Référence No. 8, "Adolescents," plus one table ("Apprentis et Adolescents"), 1950 October (Box 1)
  - 2) UMHK, Department MOI, Instruction de Référence No. 7, "Engagement, Classification et Promotion des Travailleurs sortis des Diverses Etablissements Scolaires,", 1950 October; 6 p.
  - 3) UMHK, Service d'Afrique, Département MOI, Aide-Mémoire, Fascicule VI, Classification des Emplois Remplis par les Indigenes, Brochure VI A, "Principes Generaux et Système Employé pour Classer les Emplois d'Usine et d'Atelier,", 1946 March; 9 p.
  - 4) Recensement de la Main d'Oeuvre Indigène (MOI) au 31/7/50, circa 1950; 6 p. (mimeo).
  - 5) UMHK, Département MOI, Rapport sur la Grève des Travailleurs de l'Union Minière, by E. Rolus, n.p., undated; 6 p. (mimeo).
  - 6) G. Lievens, Lettre ouverte à Monsieur Rolus, Dirigeant de la MOI à l'UMHK, 1947 December 9; 2 p.
  - 7) Dossier Lievens, contains 1) Note Historique sur le Massacre de Lubumbashi..., 2) "Assassinat au Congo Belge: Ouvriers de la Mine Tués" (Extrait du Bulawayo Chronicle), 3) Letter from Lievens to the Minister of Colonies, Tillier, 1953 April 8; 17 p. (typescript).
  - 8) Communications Confidentielles entre..., n.p. (Elizabethville?), 1951 September 15; 4 p. (typescript).
  - 9) Compagnie Geómines, Service d'Afrique, Manono, Main d'Oeuvre Indigene, 5 p. (typescript).
  - 10) Réunion de Tentative de Conciliation être Conakat et Fedeka tenue au Domicile de Monsieur Musengeshi Laurent, Bourgmestre de la Commune de Ruashi, Eville, Elizabethville, 1959 October 10; 5 p. (typescript).
  - 11) Rapport de la Commission pour l'Etude des Problèmes Financiers du Congo, Exemplaire No. 11, 1959 August 6; 18 p., plus Annexes II, III, IV, V (mimeo).
  - 12) UCOL (Union pour la Colonisation), Doctrine Politique élaborée par le Comité Central de l'Ucol en Juillet 1956 et Avril 1957, Elizabethville, 1956 July, 1957 April; 6 p. (mimeo).
  - 13) Association Lulua-Frères, Rapport du Secrétariat sur l'Activite de l'Association Lulua-Frères, Exercice du 1 janvier au 31 décembre 1956, Elizabethville, 1957; 6 p. (carbon copy of typescript).
  - 14) Congo Belge, Administration de la Sûreté, Notice Relative à l'Association Lulua-Frères, n.p. (Elizabethville?), contains listing of Lulua-Freres members in Elizabethville with their social backgrounds, undated; 50 p. (mimeo).
  - 15) Province du Kasai, Administration de la Sûreté, Bulletin d'Information, Luluabourg, Objet: Activité Kalamba et Association Lulua-Frères, 1958 February 2; 12 p. (mimeo).
  - 16) Fedekaleo (Federation Kasaienne de Leopoldville), document containing data re historical development of the association, its organization, and listing of the "associations primaires" included in the Fedekaleo, n.p., undated; 23 p. (xerox of mimeo).
  - 17) Rapport sur le meeting politique tenu par Nguba Théodore, Président Cerea, section Kipaka, à Kabumbu le dimanche, 4-10-1959 à 10 heures, n.p., undated; 3 p. (typescript).
  - 18) Province du Kivu, District du Sud-Kivu, Territoire d'Uvira, Poste de Luvungi, Rapport Administratif concernant un meeting de la CEREA tenu a Luvungi (Plaine des Sports), le 10-10-59, by Chef de Poste M. Vandegenuchte, 1959 October 11; 3 p. (typescript).
  - 19) Union Katangaise, Groupement d'Action Politique, Sociale et Economique, Projet de Programme d'Action, Elizabethville, 1958 April; 7 p. (typescript).
  - 20) Congo Belge, Quartier General de la Force Publique, Etat Major, Section G2, Luluabourg, Objet: Propagande Politique en District Kabinda, Territoire Bakwanga, 1959 September 18; 2 p. (photo of document in reduced format, 3x6).
  - 21) Mouvement Congolais, Secteur Shabunda, Direction de Kazembe et ses sections locales, "Devoir de Tout Congolais; Paroles pouvant avoir force d'Obligation pour tout Congolais" ("Manene Inawayeza Kusimama Kwa Wacongamani wote"), original text in Swahili, and translation into French, Shabunda, undated; 2 p.
  - 22) Statuts du Mouvement National Congolais, MNC, n.p., undated; 7 p. (mimeo).
  - 23) Rolus, A Propos du Rendement de la Main d'oeuvre Indigène, n.p., undated; 18 p. (typescript).
  - 24) Alliance Rurale Progressiste (Mapatano Ya Nakulima Wenyi Kutaka Kuendelea), Statutes, n.p., undated; 4 p. (mimeo).
  - 25) Jean Brabon, Bref Résumé de la Vie de la "Balubakat" depuis sa création jusqu'au 30 juin 1960, n.p., undated; 8 p. (typescript).
  - 26) Association Générale des Baluba du Katanga, "Balubakat," Elizabethville, (exchange of official correspondence regarding the statutes of the organization), 1959 February 5; 5 p. (typescript).
  - 27) Accord Conakat-Balubakat, Bruxelles, 1960 February 9; 4 p. (typescript).
  - 28) British Consulate, Elizabethville, Letter to Provincial Governor, 1954 July 6; 1 p.
  - 29) Commissariat Général à l'Information, Bureau de Documentation, Léopoldville, Notice sur le Mouvement National Congolais (MNC), Document No. 76, Leopoldville, 1960 June 16; 9 p. (typescript).
  - 30) Récit des Evénements de Stanleyville, Anon, n.p., undated; 4 p. (typescript).
  - 31) Association Générale des Baluba du Katanga (Déclaration de Mr. Jason Sendwe), Bruxelles, 1958 October; 3 p. (typescript).
  - 32) A Propos des Débats sur l'Enseignement au Conseil du Gouvernement, by Ph. K. (Philippe Kanza?), n.p., undated; 4 p. (typescript).
  - 33) Tradution (sic), Pétition from Comités de Fédération Baluba Centraux du Congo Belge au Katanga to Monsieur le Gouverneur de Province, Elizabethville, 1958 January 10; 1 p. (typescript).
  - 34) District de l'Uele, Secretariat, 20/46/AIMO/A. II.1., re: Chefferie Monganzulu, Punition Chef Abongovala, by A.T. J.J. Van De Velde, Buta, 1940 September 13; 1 p. (typescript).
  - 35) Histoire de la Sous-Chefferie Kashobwe, racontee par Kinke, Malyoko, Mutara et Mumbi, Bayeke temoins occulaires des faits a Monsieur l'administrateur territorial principal Carpentier, en presence de Kaindu Mwene, etc..., n.p., undated (1928?); 12 p. (typescript).
  - 36) Traduction en français d'un texte stencile en Kikongo, n.p., undated; 2 p. (typescript).
  - 37) Mémorandum remis à Monsieur le Ministre du Congo et du Ruanda-Urundi by L.J. Yumbu, Bruxelles, 1959 April 4; 3 p. (typescript).
  - 38) Rapport de la Délégation de la Mission de Discipline et de Paix Chargée de Régler le Différend Taty-Kini à Tshela, Leopoldville, 1960 March 28; 15 p. (mimeo).
  - 39) Alliance des Bakongo (Abako), Procès Verbal de la Fête Inaugurale de la Section Abako(?) Inga en date du 12 Mars 1960, Leopoldville, 1960 March 16; 8 p. (mimeo).
  - 40) Salut du Peuple par l'Abako, Kodia, Leopoldville, 1960 June 5; 13 p. (mimeo).
  - 41) Kinkulu Kia Bakongo, Luzitu Lua Bakongo (Foreword signed "La Direction Générale de l'institut Lumbu Lu Ne Kongo"; contains data re history of Kongo Kingdom), n.p., undated; 8 p. (mimeo).
  - 42) Abako, Congres de Kisantu (contains text of resolution), Kisantu, 1959 December 27; 10 p. (mimeo).
  - 43) Comité Spécial du Katanga, Comité National du Kivu. Contains "Note sur le Comité Spécial du Katanga et le Comité National du Kivu," n.p., undated; 20 p., plus Appendix ("Recapitulation") (mimeo). (Box 2)
  - 44) Pierre R.K. Nzongola, Recueil de Quelques Proverbes Tshiluba-Francais, Gandajika, 1962; 19 p. (mimeo).
  - 45) Note by H. Rosy, ex-Provincial Secretary of Katanga Province, n.p., (Bruxelles?), undated (1960?); 25 p. (typescript, xerox).
  - 46) Congo Belge, Province du Kivu, Services des AIMO, Circular No. 211/12465, Objet: Politique à Suivre à l'egard des mouvements politico-religieux, Instructions, from Gouverneur Général, Bukavu, 1957 December 23; 10 p. (mimeo).
  - 47) Congo Belge, Province du Kivu, Service des AIMO, Circular No. 211/12699, Objet: Politique à Suivre à l'egard de l'Islam (subsequently entitled "Principes Directeurs de Politique à suivre à l'egard de l'Islam"), Bukavu, 1957 December 31; 10 p. (mimeo).
  - 48) Congo Belge, Gouvernement Général, 2eme Direction Générale, Annexe à la lettre No. 39.055 du 6 décembre 1957, Objet: Politique à suivre à l'egard des mouvements politico religieux, Note de Synthèse, circa 1957; 3 p. (mimeo).
  - 49) Province de Léopoldville, Revendications Essentielles Emises récemment par les Partis Politiques Congolais, n.p., undated; 28 p. (typescript).
  - 50) Commission de la Structure de l'Etat, Rapport de Messieurs Ileo-Kitenge et Rolin, Brussels Round Table Conference, Doc. No. 3, 1960 February 5; 20 p. (mimeo).
  - 51) Aug. Kalanda, "A Propos du Régime Communal au Congo. La Consultation de Luluabourg", C.D.N., No. 107, 10 p.
  - 52) Exposé de Monsieur le Ministre de Schrijver, à la séance de la Conférence de la Table Rondr du 27 janvier 1960, n.p., undated; 4 p. (mimeo).
  - 53) Conférence de Presse de Monsieur J. KasaVubu, le 8 février 1960, Document No. 8, n.p., 1960 February 13; 5 p. (mimeo).
  - 54) PNP, L'Indépendance et le Gouvernement dit Provisoire, n.p., 1960 February 9; 13 p. (mimeo).
  - 55) MNC, Discours prononcé le 26 mars 1959 a l'occasion de l'inauguration des Bureaux et du Secrétariat Permanent du Mouvement National Congolais, Leopoldville, 1959 March 28; 6 p. (mimeo).
  - 56) Abako, Déclaration de tous les Bakongos, etc. "Ultimatum ou Menaces," Léopoldville, 1959 February 10; 2 p. (typescript).
  - 57) République du Congo, Ministère de l'Information et des Affaires Culturelles, Document No. 82, "Notice sur le PNP," Leopoldville, undated; 3 p. (mimeo).
  - 58) Balubakat (Anonymous), document summing up goals, date of foundations, internal rifts, etc., n.p., undated; 1 p. (typescript).
  - 59) Extraits de l'article paru dans le journal "Le Peuple," No. 292, 1959 December 8; 4 p. (mimeo).
  - 60) Abako, Tous les Bakongo sont-ils d'accord avec l'Abako(?) Tract, Leopoldville, 1959 September 19; 3 p. (typescript).
  - 61) Parti Social Chrétien, Déclaration du Comité National (re Congo), Bruxelles, 1956 February 12-27; 3 p. (mimeo).
  - 62) Kasavubu, Conférence de Presse, "Gouvernement Provisoire et Contrôle des Elections,", 1960 February 8; 5 p. (mimeo).
  - 63) Note remise au Groupe de Travail par Messieurs Diomi G. et Canon P. Bourgmestres à Leopoldville, Leopoldville, 1958 November 11; 4 p. (mimeo).
  - 64) Mouvement Solidaire Muluba, Luluabourg, le 9 juillet 1959, contains: 1) exchange correspondence between President MSM Evariste Kalondji and Congo Governor, 4 p.; 2) Letter from Evariste Kalondji to Presidents of Belgian Senate and Chamber of Representatives, 9 juillet 1959, 5 p.; 3) Rapport from A. Dequenne entitled "Revendication Lulua; Conflit Lulua-Baluba," 8 juillet 1959, 12 p. (xeroxed typescript), 1959 July
  - 65) Amicale Socialiste, Etude sur l'Organisation des Villes au Congo, 1958 May 25; 15 p. (photo of document, reduced format).
  - 66) Note Grévisse, regarding "Structure des Villes et Terminologie," "Composition du Comité Urbain," and "Caractère des Autorités Indigènes,", 1956 June 6; 16 p. (xeroxed typescript).
  - 67) Rechtskundig Weekblad, "Mr. R. Victor. Het Geval van Rechter Grootaert," No. 42, 1956 July 8; 4 p.
  - 68) La Vérité Concernant L'Affaire Grootaert ou la Libéralisation de la Justice au Congo, Anon, n.p., undated; 14 p. (mimeo).
  - 69) Extrait du Journal Horizons, "Un Important Discours de M. Kasavubu,", 1958 April 27; 3 p. (mimeo).
  - 70) Rassemblement des Habitants de l'Est du Congo, "REKO," Statutes, 6 p. (mimeo).
  - 71) Union Katangaise, Rappel des Grandes Lignes du Programme, 1958 May; 3 p. (printed circular).
  - 72) P.E.C. Ngweshe, Objet: Déclaration Changement URCO, Walungu le février 1960, 1 p. (typescript) plus "Status de Mouvement pour le Progrès Économique Congolais," 3 p. (mimeo) Ngweshe, le 7 fevrier 1960, 1960 February
  - 73) Abako, Lusaizu Kwa Bakongo Babonsono, n.p., undated; 1 p. (mimeo).
  - 74) Abako, Circulaire 1960, Leopoldville, 1960 August 10; 3 p. (mimeo).
  - 75) Anonymous, (Sûreté?), Valeur A.1 (report concerning the attendence of Weregemere, Kalonda, Ndunguka and Masudi at the Conference of the "Pan African Freedom Movement of East and Central Arica," held in Mwamza from Sept. 16-18, 1958), circa 1958; 2 p. (mimeo).
  - 76) Letter from Francois Kaninda to "Redacteur" of Courrier d'Afrique, Leopoldville, 1955 July 26; 4 p. (typescript).
  - 77) Réunion de Tentative de Conciliation entre Conakat et Fedeka Tenue su Domicile de Monsieur Musengeshi Laurent, Bourgmestre de la Commune de Ruashi, Elizabethville, Elizabethville, 1959 October 10; 5 p. (negative of xeroxed copy).
  - 78) Abako, Kangu Dia Kinkonzi Kia Besi Kongo, Direction Générale, Leopoldville, 4 p. (mimeo).
  - 79) L'Abeille, Mercredi (Luluabourg), 1959 September 16
  - 80) Conakat, Samedi (Elizabethville), 1960 April 30
  - 81) Kongo Dieto (translations from Kikongo into French, manuscripts)
    - "Le Chasseur," K.D., 1959 December 5
    - "Gloire au Chef Kanda (clan)," K.D., 1959 December 31
    - "Réalité et Pouvoir," K.D., 1959 November 14
    - "Il est toujours permis de répondre à celui qui demande légalement," K.D., 1959 December 5
    - "Triomphe du Kibanguisme," K.D., 1960 April 30
  - 82) Kongo Dia Ngunga, "Gloire et Honneur au Chef K.,", 1959 December 31
  - 83) District de l'Uele, Secretariat, No. 1292/AIMO/A.II.1, Objet: Cheff. Monganzulu, P.V. I57, Punition au chef Zabea, P. Buta, 1944 May 20
  - 84) Proportion of Fish in UMHK Af meat rations, 1936-40, D/510 Tableau No. 13 et 14 bis, UMHK Archives: A 6, Dépt MOI 8-40 etc., circa 1940
- Rwanda File
  - Books and monographs
    - 1) Anonymous, Schema General de l'Evolution de Territoires Confies aux Missionnaires d'Afrique (peres Blance) en Afrique Touato-IRSAC, Compte Rendu de Seminaire d'Anthropologie Sociale tenu a Astridu en Juillet 1951 (Astrida), 76 p. (Box 2)
  - Official documents
    - 2) Territoire du Ruanda-Urundi, Résidence du Ruanda, Compte-Rendu de la Réunion tenue, le 27 Octobre, a Kigali, 19 p.